A Guide to the Alfred Dickinson Barksdale Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10230
Alfred Dickinson Barksdale Papers 1905-1973
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10230
Mr. and Mrs. Robert H. Garbee
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Alfred Dickinson Barksdale papers were presented to the library by Mr. and Mrs. Robert H. Garbee, 1601 Clayton Avenue, Lynchburg, Virginia, on 8 July 1977.
BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH
Alfred Dickinson Barksdale was born in Halifax(then Houston), Virginia, on 17 July 1892. He was educated in local schools, with the exception of one year (1907-1908) which he spent at Cluster Springs Academy in Cluster Springs, Virginia. He attended the Virginia Military Institute from 1908 to 1911, graduating with a Bachelor of Science degree after only three years. Following a year of teaching in a Halifax school, he entered the University of Virginia Law School, and received his LL.B. in 1915. He entered the practice of law in Lynchburg, Virginia, but soon left to serve as a first lieutenant in the First Virginia Infantry --known as the "Musketeers"--on the Mexican border from June 1916 to February 1917. Promoted to captain in July 1917, he served in the 116th Infantry, 29th Division, American Expeditionary Forces, and saw active service in France from June 1918 to July 1919. Following the Armistice, he attended classes at the Sorbonne, in addition to acting as a judge-advocate for his battalion. He was released from service in August 1919, and received the Distinguished Service Cross, the Croix de Guerre, and the Chevalier Legion of Honor as a result of his military performance.
Upon his return to the United States, Alfred Dickinson Barksdale resumed his legal practice in Lynchburg. He served as a Virginia state senator from 1924 to 1928, and although this was the extent of his active political career, he formed many valuable political connections, including one with Harry F. Byrd, Sr., whom he assisted in his campaign for governor. In 1938, Barksdale was named judge of the Sixth Judicial Circuit of Virginia, this being the same position which his father, William Randolph Barksdale, had filled for many years in the early 1900's. In 1940 he was appointed judge of the United States District Court for the Western District of Virginia, and served in this capacity until he retired in 1957. Following his retirement from the bench he continued to do legal work, including service on the Trial Bench and the Court of Appeals, until his death on 16 August 1972.
Judge Alfred Dickinson Barksdale married Estill Winfree Phillips in 1934, and they made their home in Lynchburg until the judge's death. Their family included Mrs. Barksdale's son from her previous marriage, William Causey Phillips, Jr., and the Barksdale's two daughters, Louisa Estill Winfree Barksdale Loyd, and Mary B. Garbee.
In addition to his legal career, Alfred Dickinson Barksdale served on the Board of Trustees of Hollins College for over thirty years, was a member of the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia for ten years, and was a member of both the Virginia Bar Association and American Bar Association.
For further biographical information, see the typescript biography in control folder no. 10230.
Scope and Content
These papers, consisting of cat 7770 items, (12 boxes, 1 oversize folder; 5 linear shelf feet), are the personal papers of Judge Alfred Dickinson Barksdale of Lynchburg, Virginia. Most of the papers fall between the years 1938 and 1972, with some covering the earlier period of 1918-1919. These periods correspond to the years of Alfred Dickinson Barksdale's career as judge of the Sixth Judicial Circuit of Virginia and as judge of the U. S. District Court of the Western District of Virginia, and also of his military service during World War I.
The major series in the collection is that of chronologically-arranged personal correspondence, covering the years 1918-1919 and 1940-1972. This correspondence consists chiefly of personal and routine social correspondence with family members, acquaintances, and friends, many of whom were Virginia lawyers, judges, businessmen, and political figures. Prominent correspondents include Virginia senators Harry F. Byrd, Sr., and Carter Glass; Virginia governor and University of Virginia president Colgate Darden; prominent businessman, government official, and Secretary of State Edward R. Stettinius, Jr.; and speaker of the House of Representatives Sam Rayburn. A minor problem in using the correspondence is that Barksdale's nickname was "Dick," and occasionally people address him as "Richard" Barksdale.
The chronological correspondence also includes Alfred Dickinson Barksdale's World War I correspondence with his father, William Randolph Barksdale, his brother; John Barksdale, and other family members and American friends. There are also a substantial number of letters and postcards from acquaintances he made in France, including several young French women. One folder contains official correspondence concerning Barksdale's war honors.
Following the chronological correspondence is a section of topical correspondence and related materials, which include memoranda, newspaper clippings, notes, miscellaneous printed material, etc.. The topics include important court cases, organizations to which Alfred Dickinson Barksdale belonged, and major turning points in his career, such as his appointment to the district judgeship, and his retirement. The letters relating to Barksdale's appointment to the district judgeship are of particular interest as they shed some light on the processes of political appointments. Other folders contain material concerning Barksdale's World War I unit, Company M, and the "Musketeers," and material regarding Barksdale's associations with Hollins College and the University of Virginia. Some genealogical material is also contained in this section.
A major portion of the collection consists of speeches given by Alfred Dickinson Barksdale, with background material, correspondence, and miscellaneous items. Barksdale delivered speeches at naturalization ceremonies at Roanoke and other Virginia locations many times over a period of about twenty years. He often spoke to various University of Virginia alumni groups, women's groups, bar associations, and at various Virginia Military Institute, court, and law school functions. Some speeches are related to special functions Barksdale performed such as introducing Greer Garson and John F. Kennedy on the occasions when they spoke in Lynchburg. It should be noted that material in the chronological correspondence overlaps with both topical correspondence and speeches. This material was not transferred as Barksdale had filed it chronologically.
Alfred Dickinson Barksdale's miscellaneous papers and memorabilia consist of family, personal, and professional items. His memorabilia from World War I includes contemporary postcards from places he visited in Europe. Contained in this section, as well as in the section of oversized material, are Barksdale's certificates for awards he won and positions he held. Two folders contain listings of addresses of people with whom he was acquainted.
The printed material section contains printed items used in Alfred Dickinson Barksdale's military and professional careers, and printed memorabilia from the Virginia Military Institute and the University of Virginia. Three folders of newspaper clippings relate to important events in his life and career, including the trial of several German-American Bund leaders, convicted of violating the Selective Service Act in 1942 in New York City, at which Alfred Dickinson Barksdale served as judge.
ORGANIZATION
The papers were arranged to some extent by Judge Barksdale, and this order was preserved wherever possible, unless further organization was necessary to facilitate research. The World War I correspondence is arranged in folders according to correspondents, and chronologically within the folders. The major correspondence series is arranged chronologically. The topical correspondence and speech sections generally follow the divisions set up by Barksdale. In the speech section, the manuscript speeches precede other related materials. Within the two miscellaneous speech folders, each speech and its related material is in chronological order by the date of the speech. The miscellaneous papers and memorabilia have been divided into general categories, and are arranged in chronological order within the folders. Printed material follows the same organization. Oversize material is arranged chronologically and is listed at the end of this guide. Undated material is located at the end of its particular section or folder.
Container List/Series Description
- Correspondence
  - Letter: Wm. R. Barksdale to Helen & Mary Barksdale, 1905 March 5; 1 item (Box Box 1)
  - Letters: Alfred Dickinson Barksdale to William Randolph Barksdale, 1917 Dec 25 -post 1919 Jul 5; 33 items (Box Box 1)
  - Letter: Madge N. Thomson to Wm. R. Barksdale, enclosing letter, C. C. Barksdale to Wm. R. Barksdale, 1918 Jun 22; 1 item (Box Box 1)
  - Letters: John Barksdale to Wm. Randolph Barksdale, 1918 Aug 14 -1919 Feb 10; 8 items (Box Box 1)
  - Letters: Family members to Alfred Dickinson Barksdale, 1918 Sep 13 -Dec 25; 4 items (Box Box 1)
  - Letters: Misc. to Alfred Dickinson Barksdale, during WWI, from both French & American correspondents, 1918 Oct 5 -1919 June 25; 23 items (Box Box 1)
  - Letters: Wm. R. Barksdale to Alfred Dickinson Barksdale, 1918 Oct 10 -1919 May 2; 7 items (Box Box 1)
  - Official Corres.: inc. re Distinguished Service Cross & French Citation, 1918 Nov 10 -1919 Oct 20; 4 items (Box Box 1)
  - Letters: Alfred Dickinson Barksdale to Fannie & Louise Barksdale, 1918 Nov 20 -1919 Apr 22; 2 items (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1940 Mar -1942 Dec; 524 items, 6 folders (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1943 Jan-1947 Dec; 959 items, 10 folders (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1948 Jan-1951 Dec; 991 items, 10 folders (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1952 Jan-1954 Dec; 848 items, 10 folders (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1955 Jan-1959 Dec; 970 items, 12 folders (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1960 Jan-1963 Dec; 705 items, 9 folders (Box Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1964 Jan-1968 Dec; 889 items, 10 folders (Box Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1969 Jan-1972 Aug;n.d.; 532 items, 8 folders (Box Box 8)
- CORRESPONDENCE AND RELATED MATERIAL
  - re History of Co. M, 116th Infantry, Amer. Expeditionary Forces, 1918 Nov 1 -1968 Nov 22; 6 items (Box Box 8)
  - re U. S. vs. J. E. Testerman & C. K. Lovett, U. S. District Court, Abingdon, Va. - 1942 Apr, 1937 Nov 23 -1969 May 9; 40 items (Box Box 8)
  - re Hollins College, 1938 Apr 28 -1959 Feb 22; 12 items (Box Box 9)
  - Recommendations of Alfred Dickinson Barksdale to the District Judgeship, incl. by Harry F. Byrd & Carter Glass, 1939 Feb 3 -Dec 4; 32 items (Box Box 9)
  - Congratulatory letters to Alfred Dickinson Barksdale on his appointment to the U.S. District Judgeship of Western Virginia, incl. from Harry F. Byrd, Carter Glass, & Clifton Woodrum, 1939 Dec 17 -1940 Feb 26; 30 items (Box Box 9)
  - re Congratulations to Alfred Dickinson Barksdale on his appointment to the District Judgeship, 1940 Feb 15 -19; 78 items (Box Box 9)
  - re Memorials for John White Acree, Edley Craighill, Jr., Robt. Jones & Wm. Gerhard Suhling, III, 1944 Oct 11 -1948 Oct 31; 8 items (Box Box 9)
  - Letters & pictures thanking Alfred Dickinson Barksdale for his Flag Day Speech to the Fourth Grade, GarlandRodes School, Lynchburg, Va., 1945 Jun 14; 17 items (Box Box 9)
  - Recommending Alfred Dickinson Barksdale for vacancy on the Circuit Court by the Lynchburg Bar Assoc.: incl. letters of Harry F. Byrd, & A. Willis Robertson, 1956 Feb 8 -13; 7 items (Box Box 9)
  - w/ John H. Auer re John Miller & Mary Fry, 1956 Apr 2 -1962 July 25; 19 items (Box Box 9)
  - re Alfred Dickinson Barksdale's retirement from the District Judgeship, 1957 Mar 4 -June 17; 61 items (Box Box 9)
  - re Memorial for Judge Thompson, 1960 Aug 24-Dec 21; 23 items (Box Box 9)
  - re the "Musketeers", 1961 Jun 24 -1966 Sep 17; 36 items (Box Box 9)
  - re Amer. Bar Assoc. Mtg.San Francisco, Ca., 1961 Dec 19 -1962 Aug 21; 49 items (Box Box 9)
  - re Barksdale Family History bet. Alfred Dickinson Barksdale, MarthaCraddock, & Betsy Willis, 1971 Aug 17 -1972 Jul 24; 28 items (Box Box 9)
  - re Memorial for Alfred Dickinson Barksdale by the Va. Bar Assoc., 1973 Jan 3 -4; 2 items (Box Box 9)
- SPEECHES AND RELATED MATERIAL
  - Miscellaneous, 1921-1947; 11 items (Box Box 10)
  - Ms and Printed material used as reference works for speeches, 1922-1961; 8 items (Box Box 10)
  - Printed material re Naturalization, 1938-1942, 1955; 4 items (Box Box 10)
  - Welcoming the Class of 1940 into the Alumni of UVA, Finals Day Speech, 1940 Jun 8; 15 items (Box Box 10)
  - re Naturalization Ceremony speeches, inc. by others than Alfred Dickinson Barksdale, 1940-1960; 23 items (Box Box 10)
  - re Va., WWII and World Peace delivered to the Soc. of Virginians in N.Y., 1943 Dec 10; 32 items (Box Box 10)
  - re "The Practical Application of the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure" delivered to the Judicial Section, Va. State Bar Assoc., 1946 Sep 17; 13 items (Box Box 10)
  - Misc., 1950-1966; 13 items (Box Box 10)
  - re Brotherhood, delivered over Radio as Chairman of Brotherhood Week in Lynchburg, Va., 1951 Feb 18 -25; 28 items (Box Box 11)
  - re Court System and Jury Service delivered toWomen's Clubs of Lynchburg, Roanoke, and Halifax, Va., 1951 Feb 23;1955 Dec 13;1955 Feb 11; 5 items (Box Box 11)
  - Intro. of Sen. John F. Kennedy to a Lynchburg, Va. audience, ca 1956 -1957; 1 item (Box Box 11)
  - Remarks at dedication of new Court House at Abingdon, Va., 1960 May 26; 55 items (Box Box 11)
  - Welcoming the Class of 1917 into the Thomas Jefferson Society, 1967 May 5; 11 items (Box Box 11)
- MISCELLANEOUS PAPERS AND MEMORABILIA
  - Barksdale Family, biographical and genealogicalmaterial, ca [1893],1925 -1972; 14 items (Box Box 11)
  - WWI incl. re Crox de Guerre & Distinguished Service Cross, ca 1919, [1927]; 17 items (Box Box 11)
  - Professional, ca 1940 -1956; 19 items (Box Box 11)
  - Addresses, 1941-1967, n.d.; 83 items (Box Box 11)
  - re Barksdale & Uva Board of Visitors, 1947 -1956; 3 items (Box Box 11)
  - Passenger lists from Legal Conferences, w/Names & Addresses, 1952 -1957; 4 items (Box Box 11)
  - Certificates, 1954 -1969; 4 items (Box Box 11)
  - Personal, 1965 Jun 9, n.d.; 5 items (Box Box 11)
- PRINTED MATERIAL
  - Manuals, Biographies and Journal of the General Assembly of Virginia, 1897-1946; 6 items (Box Box 11)
  - Newspaper Clipping re William Randolph Barksdale, 1907 Jun 25; 1 item (Box Box 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings re WWI, 1918 Dec 19 -1919 Jul 12; 7 items (Box Box 11)
  - General Orders, War Dept. and Infantry Drill Regulations (Provisional) American Expeditionary Forces, 1918-1919; 2 items (Box Box 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1936 Oct 11-1970 Oct 22; 69 items (Box Box 12)
  - Misc., 1940-1955; 11 items (Box Box 12)
  - Alfred Dickinson Barksdale's introduction of Greer Garson at Lynchburg Bond Sale, in The Iron Worker, 1942 Sep, Dec; 2 items (Box Box 12)
  - Misc., 1962 -1972; 8 items (Box Box 12)
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL
  - Bachelor of Science Degree awarded to Barksdale by the Virginia Military Institute, 21 June 1911, Diploma (Box Oversize)
  - appointing Barksdale a First Lieutenant (Virginia) in the National Guard, 5 August 1717, Certificate (Box Oversize)
  - awarding the Croix de Guerre to Barksdale, 9 December 1924, Certificate (Box Oversize)
  - awarding the Distinguished Service Cross to Barksdale, 10 December 1924; Certificate
  - appointing Barksdale United States District Judge, Western District of Virginia, 19 December 1939, Certificate (Box Oversize)
  - appointing Barksdale United States District Judge, Western District of Virginia, 5 February 1940, Certificate (Box Oversize)
  - Barter Theater Award Luncheon for Henry Fonda, 4 May 1948, Photograph (Box Oversize)
  - appointing Barksdale to the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia, 1946-1948, 1948-1952, 1952-1956, Certificates (Box Oversize)
  - commissioning Barksdale a Kentucky Colonel, 8 May 1961, Certificate (Box Oversize)
  - "The Hung Jury" by J. T. Brett, Print (Box Oversize)
  - "Rules for Judicial Conduct" by Sir Matthew Hale, Kt., Poster (Box Oversize)